<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<MagicProperty xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
  <AttunementFeatures />
  <CarryFeatures>
    <Feature>
      <Keywords />
      <Name>Manual of Stone Golems</Name>
      <Text>This tome contains information and incantations necessary to make a clay golem. To decipher and use the manual, you must be a spellcaster with at least two 5th-level spell slots. A creature that can't use a manual of golems and attempts to read it takes 6d6 psychic damage.
To create a stone golem, you must spend 90 days, working without interruption with the manual at hand and resting no more than 8 hours per day. You must also pay 80,000 gp to purchase supplies.
Once you finish creating the golem, the book is consumed in eldritch flames. The golem becomes animate when the ashes of the manual are sprinkled on it. It is under your control, and it understands and obeys your spoken commands.</Text>
      <Level>0</Level>
      <Hidden>false</Hidden>
      <NoDisplay>false</NoDisplay>
      <Action>Hidden</Action>
      <Prerequisite />
    </Feature>
  </CarryFeatures>
  <EquipFeatures />
  <AttunedEquipFeatures />
  <OnUseFeatures />
  <AttunedOnUseFeatures />
  <Requirement>Wondrous Item</Requirement>
  <Name>Manual of Stone Golems</Name>
  <Description>This tome contains information and incantations necessary to make a particular type of golem. The GM chooses the type or determines it randomly. To decipher and use the manual, you must be a spellcaster with at least two 5th-level spell slots. A creature that can't use a manual of golems and attempts to read it takes 6d6 psychic damage.
d20 - Golem - Time - Cost
1-5 - Manual of Clay Golems - 30 days - 65,000 GP
6-17 - Manual of Flesh Golems - 60 days - 50,000 GP
18 - Manual of Iron Golems - 120 days - 100,000 GP
19-20 - Manual of Stone Golems - 90 days - 80,000 GP

To create a golem, you must spend the time shown on the table, working without interruption with the manual at hand and resting no more than 8 hours per day. You must also pay the specified cost to purchase supplies.
Once you finish creating the golem, the book is consumed in eldritch flames. The golem becomes animate when the ashes of the manual are sprinkled on it. It is under your control, and it understands and obeys your spoken commands.</Description>
  <Slot>Wonderous</Slot>
  <Source>Systems Reference Document v5.1</Source>
  <Rarity>VeryRare</Rarity>
</MagicProperty>