<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Spell xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
  <Keywords>
    <Keyword>
      <Name>concentration</Name>
    </Keyword>
    <Keyword>
      <Name>conjuration</Name>
    </Keyword>
    <Keyword>
      <Name>cylinder</Name>
    </Keyword>
    <Keyword>
      <Name>druid</Name>
    </Keyword>
    <Keyword>
      <Name>lightning</Name>
    </Keyword>
    <Keyword>
      <Name>ranged</Name>
    </Keyword>
    <Save>
      <Name>save</Name>
      <Throw>Dexterity</Throw>
    </Save>
    <Keyword>
      <Name>somatic</Name>
    </Keyword>
    <Keyword>
      <Name>verbal</Name>
    </Keyword>
  </Keywords>
  <CantripDamage />
  <Name>Call Lightning</Name>
  <CastingTime>1 action</CastingTime>
  <Range>120 feet</Range>
  <Duration>Concentration, up to 10 minutes</Duration>
  <Level>3</Level>
  <Description>A storm cloud appears in the shape of a cylinder that is 10 feet tall with a 60-foot radius, centered on a point you can see 100 feet directly above you. The spell fails if you can’t see a point in the air where the storm cloud could appear (for example, if you are in a room that can’t accommodate the cloud).
When you cast the spell, choose a point you can see within range. A bolt of lightning flashes down from the cloud to that point. Each creature within 5 feet of that point must make a Dexterity saving throw. A creature takes 3d10 lightning damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. On each of your turns until the spell ends, you can use your action to call down lightning in this way again, targeting the same point or a different one.
If you are outdoors in stormy conditions when you cast this spell, the spell gives you control over the existing storm instead of creating a new one. Under such conditions, the spell’s damage increases by 1d10.</Description>
  <Descriptions>
    <Description>
      <Name>At Higher Levels</Name>
      <Text>When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th or higher level, the damage increases by 1d10 for each slot level above 3rd.</Text>
    </Description>
  </Descriptions>
  <Source>Systems Reference Document v5.1</Source>
</Spell>