<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Spell xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
  <Keywords>
    <Keyword>
      <Name>bard</Name>
    </Keyword>
    <Keyword>
      <Name>concentration</Name>
    </Keyword>
    <Keyword>
      <Name>druid</Name>
    </Keyword>
    <Keyword>
      <Name>enchantment</Name>
    </Keyword>
    <Material>
      <Name>material</Name>
      <Components>three nut shells</Components>
    </Material>
    <Keyword>
      <Name>ranged</Name>
    </Keyword>
    <Save>
      <Name>save</Name>
      <Throw>Wisdom</Throw>
    </Save>
    <Keyword>
      <Name>somatic</Name>
    </Keyword>
    <Keyword>
      <Name>sorcerer</Name>
    </Keyword>
    <Keyword>
      <Name>sphere</Name>
    </Keyword>
    <Keyword>
      <Name>verbal</Name>
    </Keyword>
    <Keyword>
      <Name>wizard</Name>
    </Keyword>
  </Keywords>
  <CantripDamage />
  <Name>Confusion</Name>
  <CastingTime>1 action</CastingTime>
  <Range>90 feet</Range>
  <Duration>Concentration, up to 1 minute</Duration>
  <Level>4</Level>
  <Description>This spell assaults and twists creatures’ minds, spawning delusions and provoking uncontrolled action. Each creature in a 10-foot-radius sphere centered on a point you choose within range must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw when you cast this spell or be affected by it.
An affected target can’t take reactions and must roll a d10 at the start of each of its turns to determine its behavior for that turn.
At the end of each of its turns, an affected target can make a Wisdom saving throw. If it succeeds, this effect ends for that target.</Description>
  <Descriptions>
    <TableDescription>
      <Name>Behavior</Name>
      <Entries>
        <TableEntry>
          <MinRoll>1</MinRoll>
          <MaxRoll>1</MaxRoll>
          <Text>The creature uses all its movement to move in a random direction. To determine the direction, roll a d8 and assign a direction to each die face. The creature doesn’t take an action this turn.</Text>
        </TableEntry>
        <TableEntry>
          <MinRoll>2</MinRoll>
          <MaxRoll>6</MaxRoll>
          <Text>The creature doesn’t move or take actions this turn.</Text>
        </TableEntry>
        <TableEntry>
          <MinRoll>7</MinRoll>
          <MaxRoll>8</MaxRoll>
          <Text>The creature uses its action to make a melee attack against a randomly determined creature within its reach. If there is no creature within its reach, the creature does nothing this turn.</Text>
        </TableEntry>
        <TableEntry>
          <MinRoll>9</MinRoll>
          <MaxRoll>10</MaxRoll>
          <Text>The creature can act and move normally.</Text>
        </TableEntry>
      </Entries>
      <Amount>0</Amount>
    </TableDescription>
    <Description>
      <Name>At Higher Levels</Name>
      <Text>When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 5th level or higher, the radius of the sphere increases by 5 feet for each slot level above 4th.</Text>
    </Description>
  </Descriptions>
  <Source>Systems Reference Document v5.1</Source>
</Spell>