<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Spell xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
  <Keywords>
    <Keyword>
      <Name>concentration</Name>
    </Keyword>
    <Keyword>
      <Name>conjuration</Name>
    </Keyword>
    <Keyword>
      <Name>druid</Name>
    </Keyword>
    <Keyword>
      <Name>line</Name>
    </Keyword>
    <Material>
      <Name>material</Name>
      <Components>a handful of thorns</Components>
    </Material>
    <Keyword>
      <Name>ranged</Name>
    </Keyword>
    <Save>
      <Name>save</Name>
      <Throw>Dexterity</Throw>
    </Save>
    <Keyword>
      <Name>somatic</Name>
    </Keyword>
    <Keyword>
      <Name>verbal</Name>
    </Keyword>
    <Keyword>
      <Name>wall</Name>
    </Keyword>
  </Keywords>
  <CantripDamage />
  <Name>Wall of Thorns</Name>
  <CastingTime>1 action</CastingTime>
  <Range>120 feet</Range>
  <Duration>Concentration, up to 10 minutes</Duration>
  <Level>6</Level>
  <Description>You create a wall of tough, pliable, tangled brush bristling with needle-sharp thorns. The wall appears within range on a solid surface and lasts for the duration. You choose to make the wall up to 60 feet long, 10 feet high, and 5 feet thick or a circle that has a 20-foot diameter and is up to 20 feet high and 5 feet thick. The wall blocks line of sight.
When the wall appears, each creature within its area must make a Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 7d8 piercing damage, or half as much damage on a successful save.
A creature can move through the wall, albeit slowly and painfully. For every 1 foot a creature moves through the wall, it must spend 4 feet of movement. Furthermore, the first time a creature enters the wall on a turn or ends its turn there, the creature must make a Dexterity saving throw. It takes 7d8 slashing damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</Description>
  <Descriptions>
    <Description>
      <Name>At Higher Levels</Name>
      <Text>When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 7th level or higher, both types of damage increase by 1d8 for each slot level above 6th.</Text>
    </Description>
  </Descriptions>
  <Source>Systems Reference Document v5.1</Source>
</Spell>